<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Maliknyc</title><link>https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on Maliknyc</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>[Rant] Five Guys</title><link>https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/post-11/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/post-11/</guid><description>&lt;h4 id="levels-1--2">Levels 1 &amp;amp; 2&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Five Guys is trash. Their burgers are inherently flawed and cannot be good, and I truly believe that almost everyone who swears they enjoy Five Guys has either been fooled by their marketing, is trying to cope and justify them spending $20 on a below-average burger, or they&amp;rsquo;ve just never had a decent burger before.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m going to start with the fact that it is literally company policy for them &lt;a href="https://www.fiveguys.com/-/media/public-site/files/allergen-ingredients-and-nutrition-info/allergen-guide/nutrition-allergen-march-2018-us.ashx">not to season the beef&lt;/a>. Their reasoning is likely along the lines of &amp;ldquo;we want the quality of the meat to shine.&amp;rdquo; That&amp;rsquo;s absolute horse-shit. They use a standard chuck mince with an 80-20 lean-fat ratio, and that&amp;rsquo;s it. If you cooked me an A5 Wagyu ribeye — a steak that costs over $100 a pound — and told me you didn&amp;rsquo;t even salt it, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t eat it. Nobody who knows anything about cooking would eat it or prepare it that way.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>test</title><link>https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/post-12/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/post-12/</guid><description>&lt;h4 id="levels-1--2">Levels 1 &amp;amp; 2&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Five Guys is trash. Their burgers are inherently flawed and cannot be good, and I truly believe that almost everyone who swears they enjoy Five Guys has either been fooled by their marketing, is trying to cope and justify them spending $20 on a below-average burger, or they&amp;rsquo;ve just never had a decent burger before.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Free Will and Self in Buddhist Thinking</title><link>https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/post-10/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/post-10/</guid><description>&lt;h4 id="levels-2-3--4">Levels 2, 3, &amp;amp; 4&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Here, I&amp;rsquo;ll expand on the analysis of incompatibilist free will at lower levels of truth, examine where &lt;strong>compatibilist&lt;/strong> free will holds, and discuss a few alternative definitions of self to provide additional rigor to our exploration.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At Level 2, the focus is more on identifying the foundational building blocks of experience – such as the five aggregates and the twelve sense bases – without yet recognizing their interdependent and conditional nature. While these elements have a more substantial basis than nominal constructs, dependent origination and determinism have yet to be explicitly established. Without those concepts to rest upon, it becomes difficult to reject incompatibilist free will at this level, but also difficult to prove it. Although the construction of the self seems closely intertwined with the concept of free will, the very act of inquiring into the matter would bring us to Level 3. Level 1 is less ambiguous on this matter: limited to superficial naming and linguistic conventions that do not engage with any deeper inquiry into dependent arising, dependent origination is almost entirely irrelevant here. As such, if, for the purpose of easy communication, it makes sense to treat free will as existent here, then it can be so treated.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Determinism in Buddhist Thinking</title><link>https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/post-9/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/post-9/</guid><description>&lt;h4 id="level-3">Level 3&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Here, I&amp;rsquo;m going to go examine a few ways of proving where &lt;strong>incompatibilist&lt;/strong> free will holds in our &lt;a href="https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/post-7/">truth hierarchy&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s important to remember that incompatibilism does not entail determinism, but rather that free will and determinism are mutually exclusive. Thus, if we can establish that Buddhism describes determinism at some levels of truth, we can also establish that incompatibilist free will does not hold at those levels. Because Level 4 is based on realization rather than principles and introduces concepts of emptiness that undermine principled analyses of phenomena, exploring determinism – which relies on deductive reasoning – at this level or beyond may not be particularly meaningful. Instead, we should focus on Level 3 truths, which are in themselves based on cause and effect.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Two Definitions of Free Will</title><link>https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/post-8/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/post-8/</guid><description>&lt;h4 id="levels-2--3">Levels 2 &amp;amp; 3&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s quite frustrating to watch people who &lt;strong>think&lt;/strong> they&amp;rsquo;re at odds in a free will debate, but instead of delving into an actual disagreement, they&amp;rsquo;re just using different frameworks to describe what is — and isn&amp;rsquo;t — free will. Let&amp;rsquo;s minimize such confusion by laying out two of the most prominent definitions of free will, both of which are perfectly valid, but may hold at different levels of truth.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Five Levels of Truth</title><link>https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/post-7/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/post-7/</guid><description>&lt;h4 id="level-3">Level 3&lt;/h4>
&lt;h1 id="about-the-framework">About the Framework&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s talk a bit more about the Five Truths Framework I decided to structure this site around. As mentioned in the first post, the framework I&amp;rsquo;m using is based on Nāgārjuna&amp;rsquo;s Two Truths doctrine, a concept central to Mahāyāna Buddhism. Although similar ideas can be traced back to pre-Buddha times (Yajnavalkya 2008, III.2.3.6), the doctrine was largely established in Nāgārjuna’s &lt;em>Mūlamadhyamakakārikā&lt;/em> (MMK) around 150 CE, which distinguished between two categories of truth:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>[BBM 5] Limitations &amp; Looking Ahead</title><link>https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/post-6/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/post-6/</guid><description>&lt;h4 id="levels-2--3">Levels 2 &amp;amp; 3&lt;/h4>
&lt;h1 id="betting-behavior-methodologies-5-limitations--looking-ahead">Betting Behavior Methodologies 5: Limitations &amp;amp; Looking Ahead&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Hopefully, these write-ups brought to mind a few related ideas and questions that should be explored further. There were also many limitations and several strong assumptions that need further testing and empirical validation. Let&amp;rsquo;s discuss possible next steps.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First, these methods can be used to help model the behaviors around and create strategies for betting on positive expected value bets. That is what the Kelly Criterion was made for, and there already exist a multitude of modified Kelly strategies. One of the most commonly used variants is the &amp;ldquo;fractional Kelly,&amp;rdquo; which is simply betting a fixed fraction of the standard Kelly fraction (e.g., for &amp;ldquo;half-Kelly,&amp;rdquo; you bet half of whatever the standard Kelly method prescribes) (MacLean &amp;amp; Thorp 2011). Although the full Kelly Criterion is technically optimal for long-term growth, it makes the strong assumption that the user is fully confident in their edge. As we have observed with probability weighting, even a slight misperception of one&amp;rsquo;s odds can lead to reckless over-betting and &lt;strong>significantly&lt;/strong> higher ruin rates. Although fractional Kelly strategies can be effective for managing risk, I would propose testing the Generalized CRRA Kelly Criterion we formulated as a potentially more tailored way of sizing bets according to one&amp;rsquo;s specific risk preferences — as opposed to choosing some arbitrary fraction. Of course, more empirical testing will be needed to be sure of the usefulness of the Generalized CRRA Kelly Criterion. Also, if we venture into positive expected value bets, the optimal trade-off between maintaining a low rate of ruin and high average final wealth grows less clear, perhaps calling for more attention to the average slopes of log-wealth as a more balanced metric. If we keep the time horizon restricted to a finite number of bets, the dynamic between and independent effects of varying \(\alpha\)&amp;rsquo;s and \(\gamma\)&amp;rsquo;s also grow more complex given positive expected value bets.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>[BBM 2] Probability Weighting Quiz</title><link>https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/post-3/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/post-3/</guid><description>&lt;h4 id="levels-2--3">Levels 2 &amp;amp; 3&lt;/h4>
&lt;h1 id="betting-behavior-methodologies-2-probability-weighting-quiz">Betting Behavior Methodologies 2: Probability Weighting Quiz&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Building onto the &lt;a href="https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/post-2/">CRRA Quiz&lt;/a>, we might want to assess how susceptible someone is to probability weighting: the tendency to overweight low probabilities and underweight large probabilities. For now, we&amp;rsquo;ll focus on binary gambles with risky options that offer low-probability gains and high-probability losses. In other words, we&amp;rsquo;re essentially attempting to explain &amp;ldquo;favorite-longshot bias&amp;rdquo; — an observed tendency for bettors to overvalue heavy underdogs and undervalue heavy favorites (Griffith 1949). Our setup might also bring to mind concepts from Salience Theory, which suggests that decision-makers overweight extremely — or &amp;ldquo;saliently&amp;rdquo; — unlikely events if they are aware of their possibility (i.e. we react more to possibility than we do to probability) (Bordalo 2012). The participant&amp;rsquo;s baseline preferences will be modeled using the CRRA utility function and estimated risk aversion coefficient, \(\gamma\), elicited in the prior section. To capture the non-linear perception of probabilities, we will employ Prelec&amp;rsquo;s probability weighting function:
&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>[BBM 3] Generalized Kelly Criterion</title><link>https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/post-4/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/post-4/</guid><description>&lt;h4 id="levels-2--3">Levels 2 &amp;amp; 3&lt;/h4>
&lt;h1 id="betting-behavior-methodologies-3-generalized-kelly-criterion">Betting Behavior Methodologies 3: Generalized Kelly Criterion&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Now, we can discuss practical ways to implement these risk aversion and probability weighting results for bets with varying conditions. To find a systematic way of modeling betting behavior — particularly &lt;strong>how much&lt;/strong> someone might wager given a certain bet — we can look to the &lt;em>Kelly Criterion&lt;/em> as a baseline. The Kelly Criterion is a widely recognized strategy in probability theory, financial decision-making, and betting for sizing bets in a manner that maximizes long-term geometric growth (Kelly 1956). It&amp;rsquo;s traditionally derived using a logarithmic utility function, which is &amp;ldquo;optimal&amp;rdquo; but fairly unrealistic if used for modeling general risk behavior. Given finite wealth and a limited time horizon, not everyone exhibits perfectly logarithmic risk preferences. Luckily, logarithmic utility lies neatly within CRRA family, and if the classical Kelly Criterion is the utility-maximizing solution for someone with logarithmic utility, any &amp;ldquo;Kelly-like&amp;rdquo; criterion derived from a related concave CRRA utility function should also be the utility-maximizing solution for someone with those preferences. We will try to do exactly that: use the CRRA framework to create a more generalized form of the Kelly Criterion that can be adjusted for varying degrees of risk tolerance.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>[BBM 4] The Simulation Process</title><link>https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/post-5/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/post-5/</guid><description>&lt;h4 id="levels-2--3">Levels 2 &amp;amp; 3&lt;/h4>
&lt;h1 id="betting-behavior-methodologies-4-the-simulation-process">Betting Behavior Methodologies 4: The Simulation Process&lt;/h1>
&lt;h2 id="a-single-simulation">A Single Simulation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>The main limitation&lt;/strong> of our generalized formula with respect to modeling &amp;ldquo;irrational&amp;rdquo; betting behavior is that it still maximizes utility in a &amp;ldquo;rational&amp;rdquo; way, and thus, like the classical Kelly, will still &lt;strong>always&lt;/strong> advise against placing a nonzero wager on a negative EV bet. However, one way we can effectively loosen this restriction in our simulations is through probability weighting or by introducing some distinction between &amp;ldquo;perceived&amp;rdquo; probabilities and actual probabilities. In accordance with our established decision framework, the simulation tests a single chosen bet against a bet sizing strategy each time we run it. Let&amp;rsquo;s walk through the process for a &lt;strong>single&lt;/strong> simulation. Before initiating the simulations, several critical parameters are established:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>[BBM 1] CRRA Quiz</title><link>https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/post-2/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/post-2/</guid><description>&lt;h4 id="levels-2--3">Levels 2 &amp;amp; 3&lt;/h4>
&lt;h1 id="betting-behavior-methodologies-1-crra-quiz">Betting Behavior Methodologies 1: CRRA Quiz&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s look at a way to assess someone&amp;rsquo;s risk-aversion level. The plan involves developing a quiz (or experimental task) that asks participants to choose between several safe and risky options. By analyzing their choices, we can estimate their &lt;em>risk-aversion coefficient&lt;/em>, \(\gamma\), using the constant relative risk aversion (CRRA) utility framework defined as:&lt;/p>
$$
 u(W) = \begin{cases}
 \frac{W^{1-\gamma} - 1}{1 - \gamma} &amp; \text{for } \gamma\geq0, \gamma\neq1\\
 \ln(W) &amp; \text{for } \gamma = 1
 \end{cases}
$$&lt;p>Where:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>About This Blog</title><link>https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/test-post/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://maliknyc.github.io/karmagambler.github.io/posts/test-post/</guid><description>&lt;h4 id="levels-1--2">Levels 1 &amp;amp; 2&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Hi! This blog is my way of documenting some of my thoughts, research ideas, opinions, and more. It&amp;rsquo;s much more for myself, but if you&amp;rsquo;re here, welcome! Feel free to send me any thoughts or critiques at my email: &lt;a href="mailto:felixliangnyc@gmail.com">felixliangnyc@gmail.com&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There&amp;rsquo;s no rigid theme, but my current interests are largely divided between:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Metaphyiscs — the philosophy of self, free will, Buddhist philosophy&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Betting — risk behavior, betting strategies, prediction markets&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>A bit about me: I&amp;rsquo;m a college student studying economics who&amp;rsquo;s trying to learn more about:&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>